Finding aid to the Frances H. Johnson Papers. CA.MS.00313
Smith College Archives
Frances H. Johnson Papers
1885-1947
Smith College Archives
Johnson, Frances H.
CA.MS.00313
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
The collection consists mainly of letters written to Frances H. Johnson by various correspondents including Helen Hopekirk. A few of the letters are written by various correspondents to other people. Also included are clippings, programs from musical performances, fliers, and wedding invitations as well as material related to the Hartford Philharmonic Society and the Hartford School of Music.
Biographical / Historical
Frances Hall Johnson, born in 1865, was a trained classical pianist who also taught music and was active in promoting musicians locally as well as bringing renowned performers to Hartford. In about 1892 she founded the Musical Club of Hartford, a venture which began on a small scale, with eight or so members meeting and entertaining one another at their homes. In fifteen years the membership numbered 500. Johnson served on the boards of the Hartford Philharmonic Society and the Hartford School of Music (known today as the Hartford Conservatory). In 1931 Johnson published a book, Musical Memories of Hartford: Drawn from Records Public and Private. Johnson, who lived with her sister Rose, died in 1947.
Scope and Contents
The Frances H. Johnson papers contain correspondence, newspaper clippings, programs from musical performances, fliers, wedding invitations, and minutes and other related material from the Hartford Philharmonic Society and Hartford School of Music. The letters, most of which were written by others to Johnson, pertain largely to musical matters, whether artistic or business-related. The largest batch of letters is from the Scottish-born pianist and composer Helen Hopekirk (1856-1945), who was a teacher and longtime friend of Johnson's. A few letters in the collection were written by others to people other than Johnson, including a letter from 1921 written by the composer Camille Saint-Saens to Isidore Philipp, who gave it to Johnson.
Correspondence to Frances H. Johnson (FHJ) is arranged alphabetically by author and then by date, with undated letters last. Enclosures (e.g. programs and the like) are kept with correspondence where the association with a letter is obvious. Envelopes and slips of paper with notes in FHJ's hand, containing identifying or explanatory information, are also included in this series. Correspondence to/from others is arranged alphabetically by author.
The papers include notes by FHJ (handwritten lists of correspondents, possibly written at the time of donation); handwritten notes, printed brochures, invitations, and membership lists from the Hartford Philharmonic Society and Hartford School of Music. Also included are the Memoir of Helen Hopekirk by Josephine F. Allen (Mrs. B.P. Clark); music programs and fliers from Connecticut, Massachusetts, and New York; newspaper clippings, mostly from Hartford newspapers; and photographs.
Related Material
- Johnson, Frances Hall, Musical Memories of Hartford. Hartford, CT: Witkower's, 1931
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Frances H. Johnson Papers were donated around 1945 to Smith College by Miss Frances H. Johnson of Hartford, Connecticut. There appears to be no formal record of accession apart from an announcement in the Friends of the Smith College Library annual report of March 1946.
Johnson decided to donate her papers to Smith at the suggestion of her neighbor, Mary A. Goodman of the Smith College Class of 1896. Goodman is referred to in correspondence between Johnson and Margaret Grierson, Smith College's librarian at the time.
Johnson, Frances H.
- Correspondence to FHJ from Timothy Adamowski, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Nathan Henry Allen, 1894-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Charles M. Andrews, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Evangeline Andrews, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from James P. Andrews, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from John W. Andrews, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Julia Andrews, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Edward Ballantine, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Cordelia (Mrs. Lucius Barnes) Barbour, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Anne Bartholomew, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Frances Raymond Bartlett, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from R. L. P. Bell, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from David Bispham, 1902-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General
  See also photographs
- Correspondence to FHJ from Maxine Tull Boatner, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Bern Boekelman and calling card, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elizabeth Buell Brainard, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Susan Lord Brandegee, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Stella S. Brandt, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  See also Helen Hopekirk
- Correspondence to FHJ from Ruth B. Breen, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Howard Brockway, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen E. Brown and notes, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Maida L. Bryant, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mrs. Bunce, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Louise Bushnell, 189? (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Card to FHJ from Ruth and Ralph Butter, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elizabeth (Libby) Butterworth, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from John Spencer Camp, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Katie Camp, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Blanche M. Channing, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from J. Chapart, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Kitty Chatham, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Emily Cheney, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mary B. Cheney, 1898-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Ruth Cheney, 1900-? (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Winifred Christie, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Clara Clemens, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Josephine Collins, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mary Patricia Richter Collins and Christmas card, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Billy Conklin and programs, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Edith Conklin, 1928-? (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Edith Conklin (daughter), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Sally Conklin, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Carolyn D. Conning, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Katharine Conning, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Katherine Cook, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Alice Cooley, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Charles Cooley, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Paul W. Cooley, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Alf Cortot, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Persis Cox and flier, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Walter Damrosch and fliers, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  See also Felicia Gifton
- Correspondence to FHJ from Bertha P. Dennis, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen Diedrichs, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Olin Downes, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Robert Duellner, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Card to FHJ from Bessie Dunham, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen B. Edwards, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Charles A. Ellis, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Alice Falcott, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Betty Ferguson, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Eleanor Ferguson, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Peggy Ferguson, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elliot S. Foote, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Anita P. Forbes, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Gertrude Fothergill, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Fanny Thompson French, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Heinrich Gebhard and calling cards, 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Felicia Gifton, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  See also Walter Damrosch
- Correspondence to FHJ from L. B. Gilchrist, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Philip Goepp, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Belle Goodwin, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elizabeth (Mrs. Walter) Goodwin, 19?? (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Fanny Goodwin, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from James J. Goodwin, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from C. L. Graff, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Margaret S. Grierson, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Alice Haight, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Clarissa Hall, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Marguerite Hall, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from W. C. Hammond, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Jane Hastie, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Julia Havemeyer, 1901-1924; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Phil Hewes, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from E. C. Higginson, 1896-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Dotha Bushnell Hillyer, 1899-1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Lucy Hillyer, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Invitation to wedding of Harold Goodwin Holcombe, Jr., to Helene Jeanne Guyen, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen Hopekirk, 1900-1941; undated (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  Gaps in dates 1910-1911. See also William Wilson and "Memoir of Helen Hopekirk" by Josephine Allen
- Correspondence to FHJ from Greta Horn, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Arthur Judson, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Harrison Keller, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Invitation to wedding of Victoria Amelie Kneisel to Willem Willeke, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Maisy Lawherd, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Dorothy W. Lewis, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elisabeth (Mrs. Vachel) Lindsay, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Charlie Little, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Invitation to wedding of Renee Longy to Georges Miquelle, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Hamilton G. Macdougall, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Marian MacDowell, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from "Mackie" MacElroy, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Marjorie MacKenzie, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from William Mason, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Tsuya Matsuki, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Frances McCook, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from David McKeith, Jr., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Miriam (Mrs. David, Jr.) McKeith, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Albion Metcalfe, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mary Michna, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Frederica Mitchell, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Emily Morgan, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Constance Morse, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence from A. F. Motte La Croix, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Homer Norris and programs, 1904?-1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from O'Dell, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Lois (Mrs. Remsen B.) Ogilby, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Eva J. O'Meara, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Cary Page, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Richmond Peck Paine, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Zoe W. Palmer, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Katharine B. Parsons, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mattie (Martha) Peck, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Olga Perkins, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Hattie Phelps, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Isidore Philipp, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Caroline A. Pierce, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Richard Platt, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Card to FHJ from Jean Potter, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mary (Mrs. Waldo) Pratt, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Waldo S. Pratt, 1898-1899; 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Francis C. Prout, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Emily Rand, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen Ranney, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Richy (Mrs. Waldo) Richards, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from John Roberts, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elaine Bartlett Robertson, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elsie H. J. Robinson, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from E. Robinson, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Henry S. Robinson, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Marion (Mrs. Henry S.) Robinson, 1926; 1944? (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Lt. Henry S. (Bob) Robinson, Jr. and concert ticket, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Timmy Robinson, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Henry M. Rogers, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Betty Rose, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Charles Edward Russell, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Henry P. Schauffer, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen Scranton, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mary B. H. Seaverns, 1926-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from W. T. Sedgwick, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Frances Seymour, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Katherine D. Seymour, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Peter Seymour, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Harry Rowe Shelley, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Bruce Simonds and flier, magazine clipping, 1923-1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Invitation to wedding of Elisabeth Treat Simonds to Alfred Warren Burns, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Bessie Smart, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Agnes Smith and program, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Ethel Walker Smith, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Hilda Smith, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Henry M. Sperry, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elizabeth (Liddy) Stevens, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Eliza J. Stowe, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Berthe Svecenski and note by FHJ, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Claire Svecenski and calling card, 1907-1909; 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Louis Svecenski and calling card, 1907-1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Marion Svecenski, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Sally Swett, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Eleanor Taft (Tilton), 1924-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elizabeth Taft, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mattie Taft, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Elizabeth Bradley Taylor, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Edith Thompson, 1907; 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Joseph H. Twichell, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Willem van Loon, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Nan (Mrs. Frederic Porter) Vinton, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Martha Blake (Mrs. William) Walcott, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Philip C. Walcott, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Susan Lee (Mrs. Charles Dudley) Warner, 1901-1920 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mabel C. Washburn, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Mary W. Watkinson, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Gerald B. Webb, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Archibald A. Welch, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Frances (Mrs. Stanley Burnham) Weld, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Charlotte White, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Leslie D. Whitham, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Helen Howard Whiting, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from L. Annie Whitney, 1898-1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Bumble (E.T.) Williams, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Eugene E. Wilson, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence to FHJ from William Wilson, 1904-1919 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Sally Winter, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ from Chris. A. Wolf, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence to FHJ (names unclear or incomplete) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to Mrs. Andrews from David Bispham, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to S.L. Warner from John Spencer Camp, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to Mr. Welsh from F.W. Cheney, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to Mr. Editor from W. D. Mackenzie, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to Rose Johnson from Amy Pope, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to I. Philipp from Camille Saint-Saens, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to Archibald Welch from S.L. Warner, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Drawing in crayon (unsigned), 1944? (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Hartford Philharmonic Society: handwritten notes, printed brochures, invitations, membership lists, etc., 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Hartford School of Music: minutes from board meetings, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Memoir of Helen Hopekirk by Josephine F. Allen (Mrs. B.P. Clark), 1885 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Music programs, fliers (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Notes by FHJ, 1944? (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photographs
  - David Bispham, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Frederica Mitchell, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)